Guide to the Iurii Terapiano Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
I︠U︡riĭ Terapiano papers
1925-1965
GEN MSS 301
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Letters from Russian émigré writers to Terapiano, accompanied by clippings, programs to literary events, and holograph manuscripts by Russian writers. In addition there are letters from émigré writers to Konstantin Lupakov and translations by Lupakov.
Terapiano, I︠U︡riĭ, 1892-1980
Lupakov, Konstantin
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from IUrii Terapiano.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
IUrii Konstantinovich Terapiano, a prominent poet and critic of the Russian emigration, was born in 1896 in the Crimea. In 1916 he graduated from Kiev University with a law degree, and proceeded into the army as an officer. After the October Revolution of 1917, Terapiano joined the White Army in their unsuccessful bid to overthrow the Bolsheviks. In 1922, Terapiano settled in Paris.
Over the next six decades Terapiano did much to define the style and taste of Russian émigré poetry, what became known as "the Parisian note". In 1925 he became a founding member of the Union of Young Poets and Writers. In 1926-1927 he was an editor of Novyi dom, and from 1927-1939 he participated in the poetry group "The Green Lamp". From 1926 to 1965 Terapiano published six books of poetry and one volume of collected poetry. His deep interest in Zoroastrianism resulted in a 1968 study Zoroaster.
In post-war years he was literary editor for the Paris newspaper La pensée russe and wrote for the New York-based Novoe russkoe slovo. He died in France in 1980.
Scope and Contents
Terapiano's papers, dating from 1925 to 1965, reflect some of the breadth of his activities. Series I: Correspondence includes letters from many of the Russian emigration's leading poets and critics. Series II. Other Papers is a small collection of autographs by some of these writers. Series III. Konstantin Lupakov Papers contains materials to K. Lupakov, a relative of Terapiano, who translated I. A. Bunin and N. A. Teffi into French.
Russian literature -- 20th Century; Russia -- Emigration and immigration; Adamovich, Georgiĭ, 1892-1972; Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1886-1957; Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich, 1870-1953; Gippius, Z. N. (Zinaida Nikolaevna), 1869-1945; Ivanov, Georgiĭ, 1894-1958; Kerensky, Aleksandr Fyodorovich, 1881-1970; Khodasevich, V. F. (Vladislav Felit͡sianovich), 1886-1939; Lupakov, Konstantin; Makovskiĭ, Sergeĭ Konstantinovich, 1877-1962; Merezhkovsky, Dmitry Sergeyevich, 1865-1941; Mochulʹskiĭ, K. (Konstantin), 1892-1948; Poplavskiĭ, Boris, 1903-1935; Remizov, Alekseĭ, 1877-1957; Shmelev, I. S. (Ivan Sergeevich), 1873-1950; Shteĭger, Anatoliĭ, 1907-1944; Tėffi, N. A. (Nadezhda Aleksandrovna), 1872-1952; Terapiano, I︠U︡riĭ, 1892-1980; T͡Svetaeva, Marina, 1892-1941; Zaĭt︠s︡ev, Boris, 1881-1972
- Correspondence, 1931-60; Series I
  - Adamovich, Georgii Viktorovich, 1931-60 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    With clippings
  - Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1927-57, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Pseudonym of M. A. Landau
  - Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich, 1948 Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gippius, Zinaida Nikolaevna, 1938-40 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ivanov, Georgii Vladimirovich, 1953-59, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kerensky, Aleksandr (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Khodasevich, Vladislav Felitsianovich, 1925-38, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Makovskii, Sergei Konstantinovich, 1951-60, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mochul'skii, Konstantin, 1946 Dec 11, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Poplavskii, Boris, 1926, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Remizov, Aleksei Mikhailovich, 1934 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    With program of reading
  - Shmelev, Ivan Sergeevich, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Shteiger, Anatolii, 1938 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Teffi, Nadezhda Aleksandrovna, 1947-52, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Pseudonym of N. A. Lokhvitskaia With program of reading by Boris Zaitsev
  - Tsvetaeva, Marina Ivanovna Efron, Sergei, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    With clippings and programs
  - Zaitsev, Boris Konstantinovich Zaitseva, Vera, 1945-65 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    With clipping
- Other Papers, n.d.; Series II
  - Adamovich, Georgii Viktorovich, "Kogda my v Rossiiu vernemsia...": holograph, signed, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gippius, Zinaida, "Otvet G. Adamovichu": holograph, with signature of G. V. Adamovich, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gippius, Zinaida "Nevospitannost': holograph, signed "Anton Krainii", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ivanov, Georgii, "Peizazh": rotograph copy of signed hologrph, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Khodasevich, V. F., "Okna vo dvor": page from book, corrected and with inscription, 1925 Nov 25 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Merezhkovsky, Dmitry Sergeyevich, "Oduvanchik": holograph, signed, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Terapiano, IU. K., Review of D. S. Merezhkovsky, Iisus Neizvestnyi, 1933. Annotated by D. S. Merezhkovsky. With TLS from Mark Weinbaum of Novoe russkoe slovo dated 1947 Apr25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Notice on almanac "Smotr", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Konstantin Lupakov Papers, Series III
  Pseudonym C. Desquier
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich, 1945-47 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Teffi, Nadezhda Aleksandrovna, 1947 Sep 15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Pseudonym of N. A. Lokhvitskaia
  - OTHER PAPERS
    Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich
    - "Dubki", "Parakhod 'Saratov'": annotated and corrected pages from book, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      With note from Terapiano dated 1964 Jun 7
    - "Le Vapeur 'Saratov'": trans. C. Desquier: corrected typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Trois roubles", trans. C. Desquier: entire issue of Rêves, 1946 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Amphise la Taciturne", trans. C. Desquier: entire issue of Rêves, 1947 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Teffi, N. A.
      - "Un cauchemar: Nouvelle inédite", trans. C. Desquier: corrected TS (Box 1, Folder 31)